<resources>
    <string name="app_name">TTM</string>
    <string name="description">Nature, in the broadest sense, is the natural, physical, or material world or universe. \"Nature\" can refer to the phenomena of the physical world, and also to life in general. The study of nature is a large, if not the only, part of science. Although humans are part of nature, human activity is often understood as a separate category from other natural phenomena.\n </string>

    <string name="point1_title">Utilization of available resources- an Action oriented programme</string>
    <string name="point2_title">Setting up a consumer cooperative store, a consumer outlet for purchase of day  to day consumption items</string>
    <string name="point3_title">Capacity building of rural women in tailoring</string>
    <string name="point4_title">Evaluation of Smokeless Chulhas installed</string>
    <string name="point5_title">Capacity building on income generating avenues</string>
    <string name="point6_title">Capacity building on income generating avenues</string>
    <string name="point7_title">Fuel Saving Technology-Thermal Efficiency of different kinds of fuel woods</string>
    <string name="point8_title">TRYSEM project on tailoring (Garment making)</string>
    <string name="point9_title">Effect of kitchen organization on  time spent, distance covered and posture variations during cooking</string>
    <string name="point10_title">Ergonomic studies-Drudgery reduction in Home, farm and allied activities </string>
    <string name="point11_title">Ergonomics of Farm Women’s Drudgery- Ergonomic assessment of Wheat Harvesting and Cutting and collecting fodder Activity</string>
    <string name="point12_title">Ergonomic Assessment of Briquetting</string>
    <string name="point13_title">Ergonomic Assessment of Maize Shelling Activity</string>
    <string name="point14_title">Ergonomic Assessment of Drudgery Prone Activity Cleaning and Grading of Wheat</string>
    <string name="point15_title"> Ergonomic Assessment of Hand Operated Maize Sheller</string>
    <string name="point16_title">Vadi Maker</string>
    <string name="point17_title">Cotton Picking Machine</string>
    <string name="point18_title">Cotton Stalk Puller</string>
    <string name="point19_title">Single Line Ground Nut Stripper</string>
    <string name="point20_title">Comb Stripper for Groundnuts</string>
    <string name="point21_title">FiberKelu (Roof Tile)</string>
    <string name="point22_title">Multipurpose Harvest Bag and Capron</string>
    <string name="point23_title">AARAM - Cushioned Seat</string>
    <string name="point24_title">Harvest Apron &amp; vegetable Plucker: An Asset for the Women Farmers</string>
    <string name="point25_title">Manual Sapling Transplanter</string>



    <string name="point1_data">

        Brief background
Transplantation is the process of transplanting specifically raised saplings or seedlings on the field with desired spacing. Transplanting and planting vegetables in traditional way, is a hard job and dependent on women farmer. In addition, land preparation and transplantation should be done in a period of short time as per season. Conventional method of transplanting is not a healthy method as the farmers have to bend from waist and stoop while transplanting saplings which cause health hazard later on.  Therefore, mechanical transplanting of vegetable’s seedlings is necessary to save labour, time and energy costs and to mitigate drudgery of women of extreme forward trunk flexion. Manual sapling transpalnter is a good option for this.
Technology Description (Technical)
A Sapling Trans planter was introduced to plant vegetable saplings and was field tested for its efficacy in comparison to back breaking conventional method of transplanting. It’s a simple manual tool, having a metallic tube. The trans planter has a hole at the bottom to plant in the standing position. A pair of trowels can penetrate in the soil as well as right through plastic mulching as well. In order to operate the tool, drop a seedling into guide tube, push the shut pair of trowels into the soil, grasp the latch and handle together and lift the tool straight up. The tool was tested for planting tomato saplings. The specific advantages of using the tool are:
The operator can stand straight (no need to bend down) for planting the seedling making the process easy.
One manual planter can equal 4 person’s working at a time providing high efficiency.
It can be used with single or both the hands.
Economical and easy to operate.
Suitable not only for farmers but also for anyone who loves gardening.
How it is women friendly
The hand-held manual transplanter allows one person to plant hundreds of seedlings per hour.
This tool can be used with prepared seed- beds either through plastic mulching sheets or bare soil.
Used for planting seedlings of vegetables like, Tomato, Brinjal, and Chilly.

Performance
Convenient, time saving, improves Posture, reduced MSD
Locale of Dissemination/ Application
Rural areas of Udaipur and adjoining areas
Outcome/ Impact/ Benefits
The Physiological cost of work is reduced. Time Saved, Economical, Reduced MSD, Increased convenience.
Limitations if any
The transplanter base should be dry and field should be watered after transplanting the saplings
Photographs

Source (Author/ Organization)
DrSuman Singh &amp;DrHemuRathore
Annual Report, AICRP – FRM, College of H Sc, Udaipur
Ph 0294-2471914
Email: sumanfrm@gmail.com
rathorehemu@rediffmail.com
website: www.dmfw.org
Developed/ Tested/ Refined
Tested and Refined
Year
2015
Cost
Rs 1800-3000
(Difference is due to the fabrication material)

    </string>





</resources>